<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IB2: Integrative Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</title>
    <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>IB2: Integrative Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/media/icon_hub5cd333a9ad2ed2c4484e85fbbb63248_94796_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>IB2: Integrative Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Event</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/event/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/event/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feature and link using &lt;code&gt;slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload&lt;/strong&gt; an existing slide deck to &lt;code&gt;static/&lt;/code&gt; and link using &lt;code&gt;url_slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed&lt;/strong&gt; your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further event details, including page elements such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QBI SABI 2023</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/23-03-27-qbi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/23-03-27-qbi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quantitativebioimaging.com/qbi2023/sabi2023/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Spatial Analysis for Biological Imaging workshop.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present new results from the analysis of the spatial distribution of T-cells
in colorectal cancer. These results were obtained in the framework of the
AZV-funded &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2019_vp/&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CZEDER 2023</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/23-02-14-czeder/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/23-02-14-czeder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 20th Czech Days for European Research, Prague, CZ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oncobiome.eu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oncobiome&lt;/a&gt; project was presented at the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.czeder.cz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;20th CZEDER&lt;/a&gt;,
organized by the Technology Centre Prague.
At the meeting, Drs. Budinská and
Popovici presented the project and some of its most salient results, as well as
other activities of &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oncobiome General Assembly meeting</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/22-10-15-oncobiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/22-10-15-oncobiome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2022 Oncobiome&amp;rsquo;s GA meeting took place in Torino, IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oncobiome.eu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Oncobiome&lt;/a&gt; project had its 2022&amp;rsquo;s General Assembly
meeting hosted by our colleagues in Torino, Dr Alessio Naccarati (IIGM) and
Dr Francesca Cordero (University of Turin). At the meeting, Drs. Budinská and
Popovici presented our group&amp;rsquo;s recent results on building predictors based on
miRNA and metagenomics data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using empirical biological knowledge to infer regulatory networks from multi-omics data</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-bmc_bioinformatics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-bmc_bioinformatics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importance of tumor sampling in transcriptomics-based risk stratification</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-esmo_gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-esmo_gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of tumour morphology landscape on molecular signatures</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-eacr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-eacr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Method development and software</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/methods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We develop new methods and software tools to support us in our research. Here is a list of
various tools, as they become available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method for multimodal Bayesian data integration: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioconductor.org/packages/devel/bioc/html/IntOMICS.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IntOMICS&lt;/a&gt;
See also the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2022-bmc_bioinformatics/&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;. Author: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/author/anna-pacinkova/&#34;&gt;Anna Pačinková&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topology-based pathway analysis for RNASeq data: &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/3.3/bioc/html/ToPASeq.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ToPASeq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular portraits of major morphological components of colon tumors</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/gacr2019_vp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/gacr2019_vp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: GACR (GA19-08646S); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceitec.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CEITEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data available &lt;a href=&#34;https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/downloads/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7505364&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;directly here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solid tumor manifest various degrees of heterogeneity and several taxonomies
have been proposed for trying to group the tumors into more homogeneous
and comprehenisible categories. Colorectal cancer (CRC) is not different. In
fact, due to its usually slower progression and somehow later detection,
it acquires more mutations and manifests higher intra-tumor morphological
diversity then some other cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we investigate the CRC heterogeneity
starting with its morphological features. Using the morphology as an anchor for
tumor sampling, we explore the diversity of the molecular programs that drive
the tumor evolution. We have obtained about 200 expression profiles from over
100 different tumors, representing six different morphotypes (complex
tubular, desmoplastic, mucinous, papillary, serrated and solid/trabecular). In
addition, we have also profiles tumor-adjacent normal tisse and tumor-associated
stroma for building reference profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-results&#34;&gt;Main results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The morphology-guided tumor sampling allows for a finer resolution than whole-tumor
profiling. On the other hand, the single-cell assays are able to extract very specific
profiles from tiny tumor regions however at the cost of losing much of the phenotypical
context. The bioinformatics analyses revealed a high degree of variability in gene
expression between regions. More importantly, even within the same tumor (same section),
we were able to identify differences in major pathways (e.g. MAPK, WNT, TGFb). Since
these pathways are fundamental in tumor classification (e.g. by consensus molecular subtypes,
or by prognostic signatures), it comes with no suprise that these classifiers vary
also across regions, even within the tumor. These results call for a deeper investigation
of the impact of intra-tumoral heterogeneity on the molecular-/expression-based decision
systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colorectal tumour mucosa microbiome is enriched in oral pathogens and defines three subtypes that correlate with markers of tumour progression</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2021-cancers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2021-cancers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cytomine server is working!</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/21-06-10-cytomine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/post/21-06-10-cytomine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The local &lt;a href=&#34;https://cytomine.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cytomine&lt;/a&gt; server is up and running!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally! We have our own server for hosting the whole slide images: visit
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cpath.recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CPath&lt;/a&gt; to have a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ever-growing collection of pathology images has a new home. The
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cytomine.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cytomine&lt;/a&gt; server has been deployed locally and it
already hosts more than 1,000 slides. It enables us a faster and more
convenint collaboration with colleagues from Pathology departments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consensus molecular subtypes of morphological regions on colorectal tumors</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2021-esmo_gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2021-esmo_gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An explorative analysis of ABCG2/TOP-1 mRNA expression as a biomarker test for FOLFIRI treatment in stage III colon cancer patients: results from retrospective analyses of the PETACC-3 trial</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2020-cancers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/publication/2020-cancers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ONCOBIOME: Gut OncoMicrobiome Signatures associated with cancer incidence, prognosis and prediction of treatment response</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/oncobiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/oncobiome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: EU-H2020 (Grant agreement ID: 825410); Principal investigator for MUNI: Eva Budinska&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(from the project&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oncobiome.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In view of the world-wide epidemic of cancer, which is linked to environmental and life-style factors, there is an unmet medical need in breakthrough concepts to understand the causes of neoplasia. One possible factor contributing to oncogenesis and tumor progression that has been neglected is the microbiota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the mammalian phenotype is largely driven by the combination of host and microbial genes. Beyond its role in regulating many fundamental functions of health, the intestinal &lt;em&gt;metagenome&lt;/em&gt; appears to be dramatically implicated in cancer initiation, progression as well as responses to therapies, even for cancers developing in sterile tissues outside of the gastrointestinal tract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies on the gut microbiome have so far been organized on a small and local scale, and there is an urgent need to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully identify and functionally characterize cancer-relevant microbial species by means of robust and standardized methods to validate cancer-associated gut microbiome fingerprints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess their clinical relevance for patient prognosis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop diagnostic tools that could become part of the oncological arsenal for the prevention, prediction and personalization of cancer therapy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accumulating evidence underscores the role of the gut microbiome in health and disease, including cancer. The scope of the EU-funded ONCOBIOME project is to identify and functionally characterise the commensal bacteria of high clinical relevance. Using cohorts of more than 3 000 patients with cancer across 10 countries, project partners will identify microbiome signatures related to cancer occurrence, prognosis and response to therapy. They will also investigate the mechanistic interplay with the host metabolism, immunity and oncogenesis. Apart from fundamental knowledge, project results will lead to novel diagnostic and prognostic tests for cancer, as well as tailor-made pre- and pro-biotics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the role the intestinal metagenome plays in regulating multiple physBeyond its role in regulating multiple physiological functions that impact health, the intestinal metagenome is implicated in cancer initiation, progression and responses to therapies, even for extraintestinal neoplasia. Hence, there is an urgent need to fully identify and functionally characterize minimalist commensal ecosystems relevant to cancer, with reliable and robust methods, to validate cancer-associated gut microbiome fingerprints of high clinical relevance, and to develop diagnosis tools that will become part of the oncological arsenal for the optimization and personalization of therapy. Based on retro-and pro-spective studies, with large discovery and validation cohorts enrolling &amp;gt;9,000 cancer patients across 10 countries, ancillary to ongoing innovative clinical trials or FDA/EMA approvals across 4 frequent cancer types, ONCOBIOME will pursue the following aims: 1/ identify and validate core or cancer-specific Gut OncoMicrobiome Signatures (GOMS) associated with cancer occurrence, prognosis, response to, or progression on, therapy (polychemotherapy, immune checkpoint inhibitors, dendritic cell vaccines) or adverse effects, 2/ decipher the functional relevance of these cancer-associated gut commensal ecosystems in the regulation of host metabolism, immunity and oncogenesis, 3/  integrate these GOMS with other oncology hallmarks (clinics, genomics, immunomics, metabolomics)  4/ design optimal companion tests, based on those integrated signatures to predict cancer occurrence and progression. With high carat interdisciplinary experts, ONCOBIOME expects to validate cancer or therapy-specific Gut OncoMicrobiome Signatures (GOMS) across breast, colorectal, melanoma and lung cancers adjusting for covariates, to unravel the mode of action of these GOMS in innovative platforms, thus lending support to the design of cancer preventive campaigns using well characterized pre-and pro-biotics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical implications of intra-tumour heterogeneity in colon cancer</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2019_vp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2019_vp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: AZV (NV19-03-00298); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceitec.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CEITEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differences that exist both between and within tumours of the same cancer type are a major
hurdle towards proper patient selection for a given treatment and for developing more targeted
therapies. Depending on the perspective under which these differences are investigated,
different categorisation paradigms have emerged. The systematisation of clinical and
histopathological parameters led to the definition of the current TNM staging system which
presently constitutes the gold standard for diagnosis and prognosis. At a different scale, the
intra-tumour heterogeneity (ITH) has been a long-time recognised phenomenon, but its
tremendous impact on diagnosis and treatment outcome only recently started to be
systematically investigated. Experiments such as single-cell or surgical tumour multi-sampling
sequencing portrayed a highly heterogeneous picture of the various cancers with trunk and
branch driver mutations distributed non-uniformly in time and space. In colon cancer, while
KRAS, NRAS and BRAF appear to be trunk driver mutations, TP53 and PIK3CA seem to be
branch driver mutations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching objective of this project is to explore and characterise the impact of ITH on
the clinical decisions regarding prognosis (for stage II patients) and personalised treatment (for
metastatic patients). Such analyses require a multi-region-based tumour sampling which,
inherently, increases the costs of the experiments and may introduce - if not controlled -
additional noise in the data due to the particular choices made in selecting the sampling sites. In
order to control for these factors we propose to select the sampling regions based on their
morphological characteristics, thus a pathologist could relatively easily identify them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colobiome: Tumour-adjacent microbiome and immune profile of tumour in the context of heterogeneity and aggressivness of colorectal cancer</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2016_eb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2016_eb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: GACR (GA19-08646S); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Phase Ia/b study of MEK1/2 inhibitor PD-0325901 or MEK-162 with cMET inhibitor PF-02341066 in RASMT and RASWT (with aberrant c-MET) Colorectal Cancer Patients.</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/mercuric/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/mercuric/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: EU-FP7 (Grant agreement ID: 602901); Principal investigator for MUNI: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the 3rd most common cancer in Europe, and with approximately 200,000 deaths per year, it remains the 2nd most common cause of cancer death. More than half of all CRC patients develop distant metastases and have 5-year overall survival (OS) of less than 5% because of ineffective treatments. Increased understanding of cancer biology, coupled with the implementation of “omics”-based approaches, has revealed that cancer must be considered a heterogeneous disease. Historically, “one-size-fits-all” approaches have been standard practice in CRC treatment, but with the increased understanding of the molecular/genetic heterogeneity of CRC, it is clear that novel treatments must be developed and tested in selected subgroups to maximize the benefit of these new developments. MErCuRIC is a multicentre phase Ia/b clinical trial which will assess a novel therapeutic strategy (combined treatment of a MEK inhibitor PD-0325901 or MEK-162 with a MET inhibitor PF-02341066) to combat metastasis, improve survival and change current clinical practice for CRC patients with RAS mutant (MT) and RAS wild type (WT) (with aberrant c-MET) tumours. The consortium will go beyond the current state-of-the-art by (i) employing a novel treatment strategy targeting the biology of the disease and by (ii) using next generation sequencing (NGS) and ‘xenopatients’ to identify CRC patient subgroups who will maximally benefit from this novel treatment strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PK analyses found that giving Binimetinib with Crizotinib did not affect the PK of Binimetinib compared to giving Binimetinib alone. A Phase Ib (dose expansion) study was undertaken with Binimetinib and Crizotinib with mCRC patients, with the aim of looking at three sub-groups of mCRC patients expected to respond to the therapy. Interim analyses found no clinical response in one sub-group, though PD results showed evidence of inhibition of the targeted molecular pathways. Recruitment to the remaining two sub-groups proved infeasible due to the rarity of patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;see-also&#34;&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cordis.europa.eu/project/id/602901/reporting&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Final report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/people/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Downloads</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/downloads/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/downloads/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to IB2</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/home/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
