<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ith | IB2: Integrative Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</title>
    <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/tag/ith/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/tag/ith/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ith</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/media/icon_hub5cd333a9ad2ed2c4484e85fbbb63248_94796_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>ith</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/tag/ith/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importance ot tumor sampling in transcriptomics-based risk stratification</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-esmo_gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-esmo_gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of tumour morphology landscape on molecular signatures</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-eacr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-eacr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular portraits of major morphological components of colon tumors</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/gacr2019_vp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/gacr2019_vp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: GACR (GA19-08646S); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceitec.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CEITEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solid tumor manifest various degrees of heterogeneity and several taxonomies
have been proposed for trying to group the tumors into more homogeneous
and comprehenisible categories. Colorectal cancer (CRC) is not different. In
fact, due to its usually slower progression and somehow later detection,
it acquires more mutations and manifests higher intra-tumor morphological
diversity then some other cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we investigate the CRC heterogeneity
starting with its morphological features. Using the morphology as an anchor for
tumor sampling, we explore the diversity of the molecular programs that drive
the tumor evolution. We have obtained about 200 expression profiles from over
100 different tumors, representing six different morphotypes (complex
tubular, desmoplastic, mucinous, papillary, serrated and solid/trabecular). In
addition, we have also profiles tumor-adjacent normal tisse and tumor-associated
stroma for building reference profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-results&#34;&gt;Main results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The morphology-guided tumor sampling allows for a finer resolution than whole-tumor
profiling. On the other hand, the single-cell assays are able to extract very specific
profiles from tiny tumor regions however at the cost of losing much of the phenotypical
context. The bioinformatics analyses revealed a high degree of variability in gene
expression between regions. More importantly, even within the same tumor (same section),
we were able to identify differences in major pathways (e.g. MAPK, WNT, TGFb). Since
these pathways are fundamental in tumor classification (e.g. by consensus molecular subtypes,
or by prognostic signatures), it comes with no suprise that these classifiers vary
also across regions, even within the tumor. These results call for a deeper investigation
of the impact of intra-tumoral heterogeneity on the molecular-/expression-based decision
systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consensus molecular subtypes of morphological regions on colorectal tumors</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2021-esmo_gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2021-esmo_gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical implications of intra-tumour heterogeneity in colon cancer</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/azv2019_vp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/azv2019_vp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: AZV (NV19-03-00298); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceitec.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CEITEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differences that exist both between and within tumours of the same cancer type are a major
hurdle towards proper patient selection for a given treatment and for developing more targeted
therapies. Depending on the perspective under which these differences are investigated,
different categorisation paradigms have emerged. The systematisation of clinical and
histopathological parameters led to the definition of the current TNM staging system which
presently constitutes the gold standard for diagnosis and prognosis. At a different scale, the
intra-tumour heterogeneity (ITH) has been a long-time recognised phenomenon, but its
tremendous impact on diagnosis and treatment outcome only recently started to be
systematically investigated. Experiments such as single-cell or surgical tumour multi-sampling
sequencing portrayed a highly heterogeneous picture of the various cancers with trunk and
branch driver mutations distributed non-uniformly in time and space. In colon cancer, while
KRAS, NRAS and BRAF appear to be trunk driver mutations, TP53 and PIK3CA seem to be
branch driver mutations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching objective of this project is to explore and characterise the impact of ITH on
the clinical decisions regarding prognosis (for stage II patients) and personalised treatment (for
metastatic patients). Such analyses require a multi-region-based tumour sampling which,
inherently, increases the costs of the experiments and may introduce - if not controlled -
additional noise in the data due to the particular choices made in selecting the sampling sites. In
order to control for these factors we propose to select the sampling regions based on their
morphological characteristics, thus a pathologist could relatively easily identify them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colobiome: Tumour-adjacent microbiome and immune profile of tumour in the context of heterogeneity and aggressivness of colorectal cancer</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/azv2016_eb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/azv2016_eb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: GACR (GA19-08646S); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
