<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>azv | IB2: Integrative Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</title>
    <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/tag/azv/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/tag/azv/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>azv</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/media/icon_hub5cd333a9ad2ed2c4484e85fbbb63248_94796_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>azv</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/tag/azv/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical implications of intra-tumour heterogeneity in colon cancer</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2019_vp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2019_vp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: AZV (NV19-03-00298); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceitec.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CEITEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Differences that exist both between and within tumours of the same cancer type are a major
hurdle towards proper patient selection for a given treatment and for developing more targeted
therapies. Depending on the perspective under which these differences are investigated,
different categorisation paradigms have emerged. The systematisation of clinical and
histopathological parameters led to the definition of the current TNM staging system which
presently constitutes the gold standard for diagnosis and prognosis. At a different scale, the
intra-tumour heterogeneity (ITH) has been a long-time recognised phenomenon, but its
tremendous impact on diagnosis and treatment outcome only recently started to be
systematically investigated. Experiments such as single-cell or surgical tumour multi-sampling
sequencing portrayed a highly heterogeneous picture of the various cancers with trunk and
branch driver mutations distributed non-uniformly in time and space. In colon cancer, while
KRAS, NRAS and BRAF appear to be trunk driver mutations, TP53 and PIK3CA seem to be
branch driver mutations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching objective of this project is to explore and characterise the impact of ITH on
the clinical decisions regarding prognosis (for stage II patients) and personalised treatment (for
metastatic patients). Such analyses require a multi-region-based tumour sampling which,
inherently, increases the costs of the experiments and may introduce - if not controlled -
additional noise in the data due to the particular choices made in selecting the sampling sites. In
order to control for these factors we propose to select the sampling regions based on their
morphological characteristics, thus a pathologist could relatively easily identify them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colobiome: Tumour-adjacent microbiome and immune profile of tumour in the context of heterogeneity and aggressivness of colorectal cancer</title>
      <link>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2016_eb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bioinfo-recetox.github.io/project/azv2016_eb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: GACR (GA19-08646S); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
