<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>transcriptomics | IB2: Integrative Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</title>
    <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/tag/transcriptomics/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/tag/transcriptomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>transcriptomics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/media/icon_hub5cd333a9ad2ed2c4484e85fbbb63248_94796_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>transcriptomics</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/tag/transcriptomics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importance ot tumor sampling in transcriptomics-based risk stratification</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-esmo_gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-esmo_gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of tumour morphology landscape on molecular signatures</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-eacr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2022-eacr/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular portraits of major morphological components of colon tumors</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/gacr2019_vp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/project/gacr2019_vp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: GACR (GA19-08646S); Principal investigator: Vlad Popovici&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Partners: &lt;a href=&#34;https://recetox.muni.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RECETOX&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mou.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MMCI&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ceitec.cz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CEITEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solid tumor manifest various degrees of heterogeneity and several taxonomies
have been proposed for trying to group the tumors into more homogeneous
and comprehenisible categories. Colorectal cancer (CRC) is not different. In
fact, due to its usually slower progression and somehow later detection,
it acquires more mutations and manifests higher intra-tumor morphological
diversity then some other cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;project&#34;&gt;Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we investigate the CRC heterogeneity
starting with its morphological features. Using the morphology as an anchor for
tumor sampling, we explore the diversity of the molecular programs that drive
the tumor evolution. We have obtained about 200 expression profiles from over
100 different tumors, representing six different morphotypes (complex
tubular, desmoplastic, mucinous, papillary, serrated and solid/trabecular). In
addition, we have also profiles tumor-adjacent normal tisse and tumor-associated
stroma for building reference profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-results&#34;&gt;Main results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The morphology-guided tumor sampling allows for a finer resolution than whole-tumor
profiling. On the other hand, the single-cell assays are able to extract very specific
profiles from tiny tumor regions however at the cost of losing much of the phenotypical
context. The bioinformatics analyses revealed a high degree of variability in gene
expression between regions. More importantly, even within the same tumor (same section),
we were able to identify differences in major pathways (e.g. MAPK, WNT, TGFb). Since
these pathways are fundamental in tumor classification (e.g. by consensus molecular subtypes,
or by prognostic signatures), it comes with no suprise that these classifiers vary
also across regions, even within the tumor. These results call for a deeper investigation
of the impact of intra-tumoral heterogeneity on the molecular-/expression-based decision
systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consensus molecular subtypes of morphological regions on colorectal tumors</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2021-esmo_gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2021-esmo_gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An explorative analysis of ABCG2/TOP-1 mRNA expression as a biomarker test for FOLFIRI treatment in stage III colon cancer patients: results from retrospective analyses of the PETACC-3 trial</title>
      <link>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2020-cancers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://bioinfo.recetox.muni.cz/publication/2020-cancers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
